TTerm – Bash

Back to chapter "Shells and distributions".

Getting Bash

Android doesn't include the shell Bash, so you have to install it yourself. I recommend Termux or Debian, which include Bash and do not require rooting. But if you don't want to use them, I'll list alternatives that Iam aware of here.

Bash in LineageOS

My LineageOS 14.1 build for my Samsung Galaxy Tab S 10.5 WiFi (SM-T800, chagallwifi) seems to include Bash, but I don't know if that is always the case.

If you don't know LineageOS, it is a "custom ROM", an alternative version of Android that you can install instead of the Android provided by your manufacturer. It's very similar to ordinary Android, its main benefits is that it doesn't include all the additional junk that most manufacturer add to Android, and that you can often get newer versions of LineageOS when your manufacturer stops updating your device's Android. It's the successor of the popular CyagenMod.

I'll add more info when time allows.

BusyBox Install (No Root)

I used to use the app BusyBox Install (No Root) by Burrows, which is the smallest app that I've found that installs Bash without requiring rooting.

This used to work:

busybox=/data/data/burrows.apps.busybox/app_busybox
export PATH=$PATH:$busybox
export LD_LIBRARY_PATH=/system/lib:$busybox
exec bash

But as of 2017-03 it's Bash wont start because the library libncurses.so is missing. I sent the developer an email, but never received an answer.

TTerm – BusyBox

Back to chapter "Shells and distributions".

About BusyBox

Android's Linux layer is very small. BusyBox contains most missing Unix commands. It is an open-source collection of many stripped-down Unix commands. They are bundled in a single executable binary, which makes it easy to install.

For details, consult the home page and the documentation..

If the BusyBox commands lack features that you need, take a look at Termux or Debian instead.

About BusyBox's shell Ash

BusyBox comes with the Almquist shell Ash.

BusyBox doesn't provide a manual, but the manual for the Debian Almquist shell Dash appears to be very similar to Ash.

Running BusyBox in TTerm

BusyBox does not contain a terminal emulator like TTerm. There are several approaches to run BusyBox in TTerm:

Install BusyBox on a rooted device
Install a BusyBox binary into TTerm's internal storage
Install a BusyBox app on an unrooted device — this no longer works with TTerm

A future version of TTerm will offer a simple way to install BusyBox, for now you have to use one of the above methods.

Install BusyBox on a rooted device

If you have a rooted device, you can install BusyBox to /system/xbin, where it's accessible for all apps.

If your device is not rooted, you'll probably not want to root it just to install BuxyBox, it's too complicated and risky.

If you have a rooted device, you might already have installed BusyBox during rooting. If you have a custom ROM like LineageOS or a recovery image like TWRP, BusyBox might also already be installed. Look in /system/xbin or /su/xbin.

There are several BusyBox apps. In January 2018, the following two were popular.

Disclaimer: I've come across obviously suspicios and not so obviously suspicious software while researching for TTerm. I've researched all tools I mention to my best ability, but be aware that you must use your own judgement and only install programs from sources that you trust. And my instructions may be wrong, so don't do anything you don't understand.

BusyBox by Stephen (Stericson), with the current version 1.27.2 (as of 2018-01-08)
BusyBox for Android by JRummy Apps with the older version 1.26.2 (as of 2018-01-08)

If you install BusyBox to /system/xbin, then the default value of $PATH will first look for the preinstalled Android commands in /system/bin, then for additional BusyBox commands in /system/xbin.

If you want to call a BusyBox command cmd with the same name as a preinstalled Android command, you can call it with its full path, e.b. /system/xbin/cmd, or with busybox cmd.

If you always prefer the BusyBox commands, change $PATH so that /system/xbin comes before /system/bin.

Install a BusyBox binary into TTerm's internal storage

On an unrooted device, you can install a BusyBox binary into TTerm's Internal Storage, It's a little bit complicated, but on the positive side, I think that the worst that can happen it that you mess up your TTerm installation.

You'll need a binary for your CPU architecture, e.g. ARM or x86.

There are several BusyBox binaries. In January 2018, I found these:

Disclaimer: I've come across obviously suspicios and not so obviously suspicious software while researching for TTerm. I've researched all tools I mention to my best ability, but be aware that you must use your own judgement and only install programs from sources that you trust. And my instructions may be wrong, so don't do anything you don't understand.

The repository for BusyBox for Android by JRummy Apps with the older version 1.26.2 (as of 2018-01-08)
The repository for Termux has a BusyBox binary that also works in TTerm, but has less included commands (as of 2018-01-08)
Yash D. Saraf provides BusyBox for OpenGApps (as of 2018-02-11)

Install a BusyBox binary

The binary of BusyBox is a single file. You need to copy it to a directory in TTerm's internal storage, create the soft links and add the directory to your $PATH.

As an example, we'll walk through the installation of the BusyBox binary provided by Yash D. Saraf:

In a browser, open https://github.com/yashdsaraf/bb-bot/releases/.

In February 2018, the current release was version 1.28.0 from 2018-01-03 1253.

Download the version for your device's CPU architecture. For example, for ARM download Busybox-1.28.0-YDS-ARM.zip.

Open the TGZ or ZIP archive to extract the binary. The ARM archive contains

busybox.xz for 32-bit without SELinux
busybox-sel.xz for 32-bit with SELinux
busybox64.xz for 64-bit without SELinux
busybox64-sel.xz for 64-bit with SELinux

Extract the correct one. If you don't know which, I think you can extract all 4 and try them all, but see the disclaimer above.

The file is compressed. On Linux, use unxz to uncompress it. On Windows, you can use 7-Zip.
Copy the extracted file to the device's internal SD card /sdcard.

Start TTerm and execute this, replacing busybox-sel by the correct binary's name:

cd ~/..
mkdir bin
cp /sdcard/busybox-sel bin/busybox
chmod u+x bin/busybox

Now you can try out BusyBox commands without installing it:

bin/busybox cmd arguments

This BusyBox binary has been compiled with support for --install, so you can install it to the directory bin with:

bin/busybox --install -s bin

TODO Change $PATH.

Alternative installation

If you don't understand this section, just follow the instructions from the previous section.

If you want to separate root and non-root commands, check if your BusyBox binary supports --list-full. Then you can use

busybox --list-full

which prefixes the commands with a directory. Check which directory your binary uses, e.g.

bin/[
bin/[[
sbin/acpid
...

You can use that output to install ./busybox in ./bin and ./sbin with:

mkdir bin sbin
cp /sdcard/busybox-sel bin
ln -s ../bin/busybox sbin/busybox
for i in $(busybox --list-full | grep '^bin/' ); do
  ln -s busybox $i
done
for i in $(busybox --list-full | grep '^sbin/' ); do
  ln -s busybox $i
done

Install a BusyBox app on an unrooted device

This no longer works with TTerm since Google introduced a change with Android 7. Apps compiled for Android 7+ can only run BusyBox if they contain both the BusyBox executable and their own terminal emulator. This does not depend on the version of Android running on your device, only on the version the app is compiled for.

Termux

I'm only aware of one app that includes both the BusyBox executable and a terminal emulator: Termux, which includes a lot more than just BusyBox, and does not require rooting. But then you no longer use TTerm, instead you use the terminal emulator of Termux.

Other apps

All other BusyBox apps I've checked only work for rooted devices, but I have not checked all.

In the past, there was at least one app that allowed Busybox to run on an unrooted device and call it from TTerm. It was the app BusyBox for Android by JRummy Apps. In it, you could start TTerm via the menu icon (the icon with the three dots at the top right), then select "Terminal". That set $PATH to:

PATH=/data/user/0/com.jrummy.busybox.installer/files/bin:$PATH

and started TTerm. But on 2018-01-10 that location is no longer readable, the app has probably been compiled for Android 7+.

You can still use the app to run scripts that use BusyBox on an unrooted device, but they don't accept input from a terminal.

Ash startup

Interactive shell

When started with /system/xbin/ash, Ash starts as an interactive shell and executes these initialization files:

$ENV
If $ENV is set, Ash interprets it as a file name and executes the file.You can set $ENV with the setting Command line.

Login shell

When started with /system/xbin/ash -l, Ash starts as a login shell, which means that it will read other initialization files:

/etc/profile
This file does not exist on Android.
$HOME/.profile
You can set $HOME with the setting HOME folder.
$ENV
As described above for an interactive shell.

Copyright (C) 2014-2018 Thorbjørn Hansen

TTerm – GNURoot Debian

Back to chapter "Shells and distributions".

About GNURoot Debian

Android's Linux layer is very small, but there are several full Debian GNU/Linux distributions that run with proot or chroot.

The excellent app GNURoot Debian is a full Debian Linux distribution that runs as an app using proot. That means that it doesn't run on Android's Linux and file system like Termux does, it has its own file system and starts Debian in it. It doesn't require rooting. And it has Emacs, hooray!

GNURoot Debian has its own terminal emulator, but no extra keys. So you might want to use TTerm instead.

Running GNURoot Debian in TTerm

You might want to use an external keyboard or install an on-screen keyboard with a control key before you try these approaches, since you might need Ctrl+c. For example, you can install Hacker's Keyboard.

Connect to GNURoot Debian

In these three approaches, you start GNURoot Debian and start a program that you connect to from TTerm.

With Netcat

In GNURoot Debian, install Netcat:

apt install netcat

Then continue as in Termux, except that you must call Netcat as netcat, and stop it with Ctrl+c after you log out in TTerm.

With Telnet

You can connect to GNURoot Debian via Telnet. Below is a proof of concept. It will let anybody connect to port 2323 as root and without asking for a password. That's not something you want to do regularly.

In GNURoot Debian, install and setup as follows:

apt install telnetd
Install the Telnet daemon.
cd /usr/local/bin
Go to a directory that can contain executable files. For some strange reason, $HOME can't.
( echo \#\!/bin/sh ; echo /bin/bash ) > s
Create a script that starts Bash, ignoring its arguments.
chmod a+rx s
Make the script executable.

In GNURoot Debian, start the Telnet daemon with:

/usr/sbin/in.telnetd -debug 2323 -L /usr/local/bin/s

Start a debugging Telnet daemon that listens on port 1111. The port must be over 1024.

Because of the switch -debug, the Telnet daemon stays in the foreground and accepts exactly one connection.

Instead of login, which is broken in GNURoot Debian, start the script /usr/local/bin/s. You must specify the full path. You can't use Bash here, since the Telnet daemon calls it with a switch that makes Bash exit with an error message.

In TTerm with an installed BusyBox, do the following:

telnet localhost 2323
Connect to port 2323 on the same device. If localhost does not work, try 127.0.0.1 instead.

When you've finished testing, stop the Telnet daemon in GNURoot Debian with Ctrl+d.

With SSH

LATER I will write about this when I've found a SSH client that runs in TTerm.

As root

In this approach, you do not start the GNURoot Debian app. Instead you start the Linux layer of Debian from inside TTerm. It requires a rooted device.

This seems to work:

Start TTerm and change to root with su, or to the GNURoot Debian user. To find out the GNURoot Debian user, start it and enter whoami, then return to TTerm. On my device it runs as user u0_a81, so I change to it with su u0_a81.

Start Debian:

cd /data/data/com.gnuroot.debian/support
LD_PRELOAD=" " ./busybox sh execInPRoot

It shows two errors, but seems to work anyway.

That's it, now you can start a Debian command, e.g. bash or emacs (after installing it with apt install emacs).

Copyright (C) 2014-2018 Thorbjørn Hansen

TTerm – Android's shell

Back to chapter "Shells and distributions".

About Android's shell Mksh

Android's default shell is /system/bin/sh. Since Android 4.0 up to at least Android 7, it is the MirBSD Korn shell, also called Mksh. It has the home page http://mirbsd.de/mksh, you can also find it at http://www.mirbsd.org/mksh.htm.

By default, TTerm starts a shell with:

/system/bin/sh -

TODO The single hyphen is a leftover from TEA. As far as I can discern it marks the end of options and start of arguments. Since there are neither options nor arguments it should be unnecessary, so I'll remove it in a future release.

Editing

There is no way to get multiline editing in Mksh, it only uses one line, which is scrolls horizontally.

Use the shell Ash in BusyBox or Bash instead.

Startup

Interactive shell

When started with /system/bin/sh in TTerm (with or without the hyphen), Mksh starts as an interactive shell and executes initialization files. On my devices with Android 4.4 to 7 it's:

$ENV
If $ENV is set, Mksh interprets it as a file name and executes the file.You can set $ENV with the setting Command line.

/system/etc/mkshrc
If $ENV is unset, Mksh executes /system/etc/mkshrc, which you can only change on a rooted device.

Login shell

When started with /system/bin/sh -l, Mksh starts as a login shell, which means that it will read other initialization files. On my devices with Android 4.4 to 7, a login shell reads:

/system/etc/profile
You can only change this file on a rooted device.
$HOME/.profile
You can set $HOME with the setting HOME folder.
$ENV or /system/etc/mkshrc
As described above for an interactive shell.

Copyright (C) 2014-2018 Thorbjørn Hansen

TTerm – Termux

Back to chapter "Shells and distributions".

About Termux

Android's Linux layer is very small. The excellent app Termux is a Linux distribution that extends Android's Linux with lots of packages. It runs on Android's Linux and file system, not using chroot or proot like GNURoot Debian does. It doesn't require rooting. And it has Emacs, hooray!

Running Termux in TTerm

Termux has its own terminal emulator, but you can use TTerm instead. (Currently the terminal emulator of Termux handles resizing better than TTerm, but provides less settings, so try both before you choose one, or wait until TTerm improves. :-)

Connect to Termux

In these three approaches, you start Termux and start a program that you connect to from TTerm.

With Netcat

You can connect to Termux via Netcat nc. Below is a proof of concept. It will let anybody connect to port 1111 without asking for a password. That's not something you want to do regularly.

I found the solution on Stack Overflow.

In Termux, install Busybox:

apt install busybox

In Termux, start Netcat and a shell, connected with a "named pipe". This will accept one connection, then quit.

cd ~
rm -f pipe typescript
mkfifo pipe
script -q < pipe | nc -l -p 1111 > pipe
rm -f pipe typescript

Details:

cd ~
Change to a writable directory, e.g. $HOME.
rm -f pipe typescript
If necessary, remove the named pipe and log from a previous run.
mkfifo pipe
Make a "named pipe", also called a "FIFO" ("First In, First Out"). That is a file that connects two processes with a bidirectional pipe.
script -q < pipe | nc -l -p 1111 > pipe

nc is the BusyBox version of Netcat. It will read input from port 1111 and write it to pipe.

In GNURoot Debian you must use netcat instead.

In some version of Netcat, for example Cygwin's, you have to remove the switch -p.

script -q starts a shell that reads input from pipe and writes input and output to netcat, which writes it to port 1111.

script writes a log file typescript that we do not need. How do we avoid that?

In Termux the command stops when you log out in TTerm. In GNURoot Debian you have to stop it with Ctrl+c.

rm -f pipe typescript
Remove the named pipe and log from a previous run.

Now change to TTerm with an installed BusyBox.

Netcat does not tell the remote shell the terminal size, so look it up with stty size For example

stty size
38 84

means 38 rows and 84 columns.

Now enter this in a single line:

stty raw -echo; nc localhost 1111; stty sane

If you do not enter all three commands in one line, you can't see what you type for the second and third commands.

The first command stty raw -echo sets the terminal settings:

stty raw sets the terminal to raw mode, so that all chars are sent immediately to the remote shell, and all chars output by the remote shell are shown. That is necessary so a Ctrl+C arrives at the remote shell, otherwise it stops the local Netcat.

stty -echo turns off local echoing, so that the remote shell on Termux decides when to echo user input.

The second command nc localhost 111 connects to the Netcat running on port 1111 of the same device. If localhost does not work, try 127.0.0.1 instead.

After you quit the shell that runs remotely in Termux, the third command stty sane sets the terminal settings back to their default.

Now we are in a shell on the remote Termux. Set the terminal size so the shell on Termux knows it, for example with:

stty rows 38 cols 84

When you exit the remote shell, Netcat on the remote Termux also exits. To accept another connection, restart it in the remote Termux.

With Telnet

You can connect to Termux via Telnet. Below is a proof of concept. It will let anybody connect to port 2323 without asking for a password. That's not something you want to do regularly.

In Termux, install Busybox:

apt install busybox

Start a Telnet daemon in Termux:

telnetd -p 2323 -l bash -F

-p 2323 makes the Telnet daemon listen to port 2323. The port must be over 1024.

-l bash makes it run the shell bash instead of login.

-F makes it run in the foreground.

In TTerm with an installed BusyBox, do the following:

telnet localhost 2323
Telnet connects to port 2323 on the same device. If localhost does not work, try 127.0.0.1 instead.

When you've finished testing, stop the Telnet daemon in Termux with Ctrl+c.

With SSH

LATER I will write about this when I've found a SSH client that runs in TTerm.

Here is some information how to start a SSH server in Termux.

As root

In this approach, you do not start the Termux app. Instead you start the Linux layer of Termux from inside TTerm. It requires a rooted device.

This seems to work, except that Emacs has problems when you resize the screen.

Start TTerm and change to root with su, or to the Termux user. To find out the Termux user, start Termux and enter whoami, then return to TTerm. On my device it runs as user u0_a146, so I change to it with su u0_a146.
Set the environment variables $PREFIX, $LD_LIBRARY_PATH and $PATH:

export PREFIX=/data/data/com.termux/files/usr
export LD_LIBRARY_PATH=$PREFIX/lib
export PATH=$PREFIX/bin:$PREFIX/bin/applets

That's it, now you can start a Termux command, e.g. bash or emacs (after installing it with apt install emacs).

Copyright (C) 2014-2018 Thorbjørn Hansen